<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
     <title> New Wayland Blog </title>
     <link href="https://new-wayland.com/blog" />
     <updated>2020-07-28T07:53:24Z</updated>
     <author>
          <name> NeilW </name>
     </author>
     <id>https://new-wayland.com/blog</id>
     <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://new-wayland.com/blog/atom.xml" />
<entry>
     <title> Revealed: The Simple Change That Breaks Mainstream Macro </title>
     <link href="https://new-wayland.com/blog#Revealed%3A%20The%20Simple%20Change%20That%20Breaks%20Mainstream%20Macro"/>
     <id>https://new-wayland.com/blog#Revealed%3A%20The%20Simple%20Change%20That%20Breaks%20Mainstream%20Macro</id>
     <updated>2020-07-28T07:53:24Z</updated>
     <published>2020-07-27T16:17:15Z</published>
     <content><![CDATA[<p>As regular visitors to the <a class="tc-tiddlylink-external" href="https://discord.gg/ESGqEsv" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">New Wayland Discord Forum</a> will know, I've been working on <a class="tc-tiddlylink-external" href="https://github.com/newwayland/baseline-economy" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">replicating a mainstream Baseline Model</a> (Lengnick, Matthias. (2013). Agent-based macroeconomics: A baseline model. Journal of Economic Behavior &amp; Organization. 86.10.1016/j.jebo.2012.12.021). </p><p>This is a model that strips away any part of reality that get in the way of demonstrating the mainstream outcome. It has one commodity, there are no banks, money is exogenous, wages are flexible - particularly downwards, etc, etc. The paper states &quot;Finally, we demonstrated that the equilibrium is a robust result of the ACE economy for all markets. It does only break down, if either price or wage adjustment is turned off completely.&quot;</p><p>And the results appear to bear that out.</p><p><a class="tc-tiddlylink-external" href="http://baseline.model.new-wayland.com" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">(Baseline Model)</a> <img src="assets/ace-output-baseline.png" title="Baseline Output"></p><p>However when you look into the design of the model (Section 2.3, pp108) you notice something peculiar:</p><blockquote class="tc-quote"><p>Each household visits one randomly determined firm of those he has a ... connection with </p></blockquote><p>I don't know about you but I don't go to a shop randomly. I go to the one where I can get what I want at the cheapest price. Surely a good mainstream economist would do the same?</p><p>So let's make that change to this robust model. It's a single line change from</p><pre><code> # Put the preferred suppliers in a random order self.model.random.shuffle(self.preferred_suppliers)</code></pre><p>to</p><pre><code> # Put the preferred suppliers in price order self.preferred_suppliers.sort(key=attrgetter(&quot;goods_price&quot;))</code></pre><p>so rather than randomly visiting a supplier to see if they can fill our goods demand we go to the supplier with the cheapest price first and then the next cheapest and so on. </p><p>Let's see what the results are</p><p><a class="tc-tiddlylink-external" href="http://price-shopping.model.new-wayland.com" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">(Price Shopping Model)</a> <img src="assets/ace-output-price-shopping.png" title="Price Sensitive Output"></p><p>Oh dear. </p><p>If this model is to be believed, full employment and price stability and price competition appear to be incompatible in the mainstream worldview. </p><hr><p><sub>(Model parameters: Household Starting Money 3200, Firm Starting Money 0, Initial Goods Price 27, Initial Daily Wage Rate 70)</sub></p>]]>
     </content>
</entry>
<entry>
     <title> The View Through The MMT Lens </title>
     <link href="https://new-wayland.com/blog#The%20View%20Through%20The%20MMT%20Lens"/>
     <id>https://new-wayland.com/blog#The%20View%20Through%20The%20MMT%20Lens</id>
     <updated>2020-07-26T10:04:22Z</updated>
     <published>2020-07-26T10:03:34Z</published>
     <content><![CDATA[<p>MMT is a way of looking at the financial part of the economy from a different point of view. It is often described as a Lens you can look through to see things that hither too have not been made clear. </p><p>When looking at the banking system, that view looks something like this</p><p><img src="https://docs.google.com/drawings/d/e/2PACX-1vTcQRj3bqtjzRHIcBxEevQ9NprSNoqAVbVWlrvEZOB7xMWNcJ9hToVgZ1y2siWhjR2AXrT5N8Fm6Ae-/pub?w=960&amp;amp;h=720"></p><p>What this view highlights is the institutional and accounting realities of the financial system. It is hierarchical, and in the majority of the world the central bank is a creature of the sovereign legislature, who sets its remit - the playpen in which the central bank toddler can be 'independent'. </p><p>Other entities operating in the currency zone form a hierarchy of balance sheets under the central bank. Only some have central bank accounts. Others do not. Those with central bank accounts must act as nominees for those without. This has an important effect. It means <strong>there is an extra set of financial liabilities and assets in the system for each layer in the hierarchy</strong>. If I have an account at a non-bank financial institution and I receive a government payment that will create an equivalent additional asset for the non-bank <em>and</em> the clearing bank.</p><p>For example: I get a 100GBP asset, the non-bank gets a 100GBP asset and the bank gets a 100GBP asset for the same single 100GBP transfer from HM Treasury. Everybody then gets to play asset swap games in the financial markets with their version of the asset. All three could bid at a Gilt auction for example for the single 100GBP Gilt on offer using what is essentially the same 100GBP. </p><p>That's why the banking hierarchy matters and why it is vitally important to get the institutional structure and the accounting right. You cannot just consolidate the whole thing, abstract it away and then wonder why bond auctions keep getting covered bids.</p>]]>
     </content>
</entry>
<entry>
     <title> MMT on The Weekly </title>
     <link href="https://new-wayland.com/blog#MMT%20on%20The%20Weekly"/>
     <id>https://new-wayland.com/blog#MMT%20on%20The%20Weekly</id>
     <updated>2020-07-23T06:09:58Z</updated>
     <published>2020-07-23T05:57:48Z</published>
     <content><![CDATA[<p>Kudos to the Australian contingent getting this sketch on The Weekly. Can't see the BBC doing something like this - either about MMT or a decent comedy show.</p><p><html><iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="true" frameborder="0" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/uEqucQNLIko" width="560"></iframe></html></p>]]>
     </content>
</entry>
<entry>
     <title> The MMT Approach in a Nutshell </title>
     <link href="https://new-wayland.com/blog#The%20MMT%20Approach%20in%20a%20Nutshell"/>
     <id>https://new-wayland.com/blog#The%20MMT%20Approach%20in%20a%20Nutshell</id>
     <updated>2020-07-20T07:46:19Z</updated>
     <published>2020-07-20T07:10:55Z</published>
     <content><![CDATA[<p>MMT takes the view that monetary policy is largely useless as a stabilisation device, and what is known as the horizontal circuit (&quot;bank money&quot;) should be left to operate as a market rather than being manipulated all the time. Therefore you leave the base rate at the natural rate of 0% and stop artificially trying to hold it above that, particularly stop moving it around. </p><p>What that means is that government stops paying banks &quot;welfare on reserves&quot; payments. No Interest on Reserves. No Bond Coupons. Any income banks earn they have to get by discounting collateral in the private economy and charging for that service (aka making loans).</p><p>System stabilisation can then be done using the vertical circuit (&quot;central bank money&quot;) which is added and removed as required to commercial bank's balance sheets and forcibly creates additional bank deposits in the hands of individuals - because bank money is pegged one-to-one to central bank money. </p><p>The result is that the bank money system operates within a containment vessel defined by fixed banking policies, not ones that change month to month, and the banking system ebbs and flows within the policy boundaries, with the government's vertical system countercyclically matching the ebb and flow.</p><p>This is where the Job Guarantee sits. The wage is paid with vertical money and matches the ebb and flow of bank money spending countercyclically. But importantly it does the same thing on the production side with labour hours - injecting and removing labour hours countercyclically with private and public sector demand keeping labour hours near constant relative to the working population. </p><p>A guaranteed alternative job replaces bank credit manipulation as the stabilisation process. The production system gets a change in output, not a dead loss. You get income in your pocket, not a debt millstone around your neck. </p><p>And that's how you get to true full employment and price stability within an economic system where demand is satisfied. </p>]]>
     </content>
</entry>
<entry>
     <title> Bonds Pay For Themselves </title>
     <link href="https://new-wayland.com/blog#Bonds%20Pay%20For%20Themselves"/>
     <id>https://new-wayland.com/blog#Bonds%20Pay%20For%20Themselves</id>
     <updated>2020-07-17T12:35:19Z</updated>
     <published>2020-07-17T06:49:56Z</published>
     <content><![CDATA[<p>I note that the Hard of Accounting are out in force again pushing their fallacious line that Taxes Must Rise because we decided to use government to save the economy in the face of a nasty pandemic.</p><p>There must be Fire and Brimstone. The Sin must be Purged.</p><p>Clueless idiots the lot of them - particularly those at the ironically named Institute for Fiscal Studies who really ought to know better. (If they do study Fiscal they don't do it very effectively).</p><p>This is how it works in reality.</p><p>You receive some furlough pay, which is taxed, you spend that money at a shop, which is taxed, they pay their staff which is taxed, who spend that money at a shop, which is taxed and so on. </p><p>Imagine a stone skipping across a pond where every bounce is a transaction and every ripple is taxation. </p><p>If you expand that sequence you'll find that eventually the initial injection of money (G) for the furlough pay disappears in taxation (T). Or as it tends to be written mathematically:</p><p><span><span class="katex-display"><span class="katex"><span class="katex-mathml"><math><semantics><mrow><mi>δ</mi><mo stretchy="false">(</mo><mi>G</mi><mo>−</mo><mi>T</mi><mo stretchy="false">)</mo><mo>=</mo><mn>0</mn></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex"> \delta(G - T) = 0 </annotation></semantics></math></span><span class="katex-html" aria-hidden="true"><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1em;vertical-align:-0.25em;"></span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.03785em;">δ</span><span class="mopen">(</span><span class="mord mathdefault">G</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span><span class="mbin">−</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1em;vertical-align:-0.25em;"></span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.13889em;">T</span><span class="mclose">)</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span><span class="mrel">=</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:0.64444em;vertical-align:0em;"></span><span class="mord">0</span></span></span></span></span></span></p><p>Bonds come about when not everybody in the sequence spends all their money - aka saving. There's been a lot of that recently due to frightened people increasing their rainy day funds, people paying off loans and simple lack of opportunities to spend.</p><p>The increase in Savings (S) and decrease in Loans (I) creates a government deficit. Or as I like to write it</p><p><span><span class="katex-display"><span class="katex"><span class="katex-mathml"><math><semantics><mrow><mi>δ</mi><mo stretchy="false">(</mo><mi>S</mi><mo>−</mo><mi>I</mi><mo stretchy="false">)</mo><mtext>  </mtext><mo>⟹</mo><mtext>  </mtext><mi>δ</mi><mo stretchy="false">(</mo><mi>G</mi><mo>−</mo><mi>T</mi><mo stretchy="false">)</mo></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex"> \delta(S - I) \implies \delta(G -T) </annotation></semantics></math></span><span class="katex-html" aria-hidden="true"><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1em;vertical-align:-0.25em;"></span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.03785em;">δ</span><span class="mopen">(</span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.05764em;">S</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span><span class="mbin">−</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1em;vertical-align:-0.25em;"></span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.07847em;">I</span><span class="mclose">)</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span><span class="mrel">⟹</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1em;vertical-align:-0.25em;"></span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.03785em;">δ</span><span class="mopen">(</span><span class="mord mathdefault">G</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span><span class="mbin">−</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1em;vertical-align:-0.25em;"></span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.13889em;">T</span><span class="mclose">)</span></span></span></span></span></span></p><p>A change in net savings causes a change in the government sector deficit</p><p>Under our current regime that deficit is swapped for Bonds. Green Dollars are swapped for Yellow Dollars (treasuries), Silver Pounds are swapped for Gold Pounds (Gilts). </p><p>The Treasury or the Gilt or the JGB is just a savings instrument held by somebody who didn't feel like spending their money right now. </p><p>In our stone bouncing sequence above you can imagine the video is paused just after a ripple occurs. A Bond is a pause button in the spending sequence. </p><p>Eventually the sunny uplands will return, people will feel less frightened, go to the shops more, and break out the credit card again. And that is like hitting 'play' on our sequence. The saved money is then spent at a shop, which is taxed, who pay their staff, which is taxed, who then spend at the shop, which is taxed... The bouncing continues, creating a decrease in savings and/or an increase in Loans. Which gives:</p><p><span><span class="katex-display"><span class="katex"><span class="katex-mathml"><math><semantics><mrow><mi>δ</mi><mo stretchy="false">(</mo><mi>S</mi><mo>−</mo><mi>I</mi><mo stretchy="false">)</mo><mtext>  </mtext><mo>⟹</mo><mtext>  </mtext><mi>δ</mi><mo stretchy="false">(</mo><mn>0</mn><mo>−</mo><mi>T</mi><mo stretchy="false">)</mo></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex"> \delta(S - I) \implies \delta(0-T) </annotation></semantics></math></span><span class="katex-html" aria-hidden="true"><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1em;vertical-align:-0.25em;"></span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.03785em;">δ</span><span class="mopen">(</span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.05764em;">S</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span><span class="mbin">−</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1em;vertical-align:-0.25em;"></span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.07847em;">I</span><span class="mclose">)</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span><span class="mrel">⟹</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1em;vertical-align:-0.25em;"></span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.03785em;">δ</span><span class="mopen">(</span><span class="mord">0</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span><span class="mbin">−</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1em;vertical-align:-0.25em;"></span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.13889em;">T</span><span class="mclose">)</span></span></span></span></span></span></p><p>A reduction in net savings causes additional tax!</p><p>And there, by accounting identity, is your extra tax, which reduces the government deficit and may even eliminate it completely and create a surplus. The extra tax ensures that bonds that mature are not reissued and the rate of issue of bonds slows downs and may even reverse.</p><p>The tax arises and the bonds disappear completely automatically when people who hold the savings they represent decide to spend their savings. </p><p>The same percentage of a bigger number is another bigger number. Mathematics will still work as it always has done post-Covid.</p><p>No raid on wallets required. </p>]]>
     </content>
</entry>
<entry>
     <title> UK Employment stats </title>
     <link href="https://new-wayland.com/blog#UK%20Employment%20stats"/>
     <id>https://new-wayland.com/blog#UK%20Employment%20stats</id>
     <updated>2020-07-16T09:32:34Z</updated>
     <published>2020-07-16T09:28:45Z</published>
     <content><![CDATA[<p>If this wiki does it job, then <a class="tc-tiddlylink tc-tiddlylink-resolves" href="#UK%20-%20People%20Wanting%20Work">UK - People Wanting Work</a> should give you the current up to date UK job shortage statistics. </p><p>And that page should always be up to date - if I've remembered to update the underlying spreadsheet!</p><p>Searching for 'stats' in the search box will bring up all the wiki pages referencing the statistics I keep</p>]]>
     </content>
</entry>
<entry>
     <title> From Furlough to Full-Employment - Part Deux </title>
     <link href="https://new-wayland.com/blog#From%20Furlough%20to%20Full-Employment%20-%20Part%20Deux"/>
     <id>https://new-wayland.com/blog#From%20Furlough%20to%20Full-Employment%20-%20Part%20Deux</id>
     <updated>2020-07-14T07:26:25Z</updated>
     <published>2020-07-14T07:24:24Z</published>
     <content><![CDATA[<p>The idea is to provide real people with the ability to sell their hours automatically.</p><p>In my current design you are always on the default PAYE scheme, which kicks in as soon as fewer than 35 hours are booked to another PAYE scheme. That drops you onto the &quot;volunteer list&quot; for the unbooked hours doing the &quot;looking for a JG position&quot; job by default (a rather more useful version of the current 35 hours &quot;job seeking&quot; requirement of Universal Credit - looking for jobs that cannot exist in aggregate).</p><p>You can then contact a Work Coach to have yourself taken off that job if you'd prefer not to bother with the process, or to investigate what is on offer and get something lined up. If you don't contact a Work Coach, or they can't easily contact you, then they will suspend payment until you do. Just as would happen if you didn't turn up to work in any other job. I want the process to be automatic, and the registration and verification details submitted in the PAYE Returns by the previous PAYE employer. No forms to fill in.</p><p>Running through the usual use cases I believe this process handles full-time, part-time and temporary, whether they want to be engaged with the Job Guarantee or not.</p><p>Beyond that it's up to you. But you only get paid for hours booked to the Job Guarantee. Since there is a job on offer, you will take it if you are short of money. If you're not short of money and have savings or redundancy then you can take your time. Those with scarce skills higher up the tree will be able to negotiate those protections into their employment contracts - particularly if they unionise.</p><p>How long you can be on the &quot;looking for a JG position&quot; job before you are required to move on I've not really thought about very much (largely because I suspect everybody will want to get off it as soon as possible). I don't believe there is a time limit in Universal Credit, but given the higher level of payment on the Job Guarantee perhaps you will have to put your case to a jury of your peers after a period of time - particularly if you can choose to go on the JG.</p>]]>
     </content>
</entry>
<entry>
     <title> From Furlough to Full-Employment </title>
     <link href="https://new-wayland.com/blog#From%20Furlough%20to%20Full-Employment"/>
     <id>https://new-wayland.com/blog#From%20Furlough%20to%20Full-Employment</id>
     <updated>2020-07-10T07:41:43Z</updated>
     <published>2020-07-10T07:34:12Z</published>
     <content><![CDATA[<p><a class="tc-tiddlylink-external" href="https://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/2020/jul/08/rishi-sunak-unveils-stamp-duty-holiday-and-hospitality-vat-cut-furloughed-coronavirus" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Sunak is frustrating</a>. We could move from Furlough to Full Employment tomorrow and solve the whole problem in one shot. </p><p>PAYE needs to capture the bank account details of the employed - along with the hours worked on that PAYE scheme. That is then associated with an NI number and checked to make sure the addresses are UK based and tie up. </p><p>We then top people up at the living wage up to 35 hours per week if they have an NI number that has been paid elsewhere in the last year, but are not currently receiving sufficient money. Essentially we create a default PAYE scheme everybody is enrolled upon paid directly from the Ways and Means Account at the Bank of England. </p><p>If the self-employed want to be part of the scheme they need to run their drawing through PAYE. Giving them that options allows us to phase out and get rid of class 2 and class 4. </p><p>Then anybody who is on the default PAYE scheme is added to the famous &quot;volunteer list&quot; as labour for government to use as it sees fit.</p><p>A reserve army of workers. And the Universal Credit Work Coaches can be tasked with finding them all something to do for their money. </p>]]>
     </content>
</entry>
<entry>
     <title> Another Fixed Exchange Rate Inconsistency? </title>
     <link href="https://new-wayland.com/blog#Another%20Fixed%20Exchange%20Rate%20Inconsistency%3F"/>
     <id>https://new-wayland.com/blog#Another%20Fixed%20Exchange%20Rate%20Inconsistency%3F</id>
     <updated>2020-07-10T06:37:27Z</updated>
     <published>2020-07-10T06:26:54Z</published>
     <content><![CDATA[<p>Why do those people who agitate for a fixed exchange rate between currencies also advocate for a floating rate between government bonds and the currency?</p><p>If a move between bonds and currency needs to be discouraged by a floating rate, then why doesn't a move between a local currency and a foreign currency need to be discouraged by a floating rate? </p><p>If the Euro is such a great idea across such a wide area, why aren't Eurozone government bonds payable at par on demand at any bank in the Eurozone?</p><p>After all they are just unspent savings. </p>]]>
     </content>
</entry>
<entry>
     <title> Playing with Hypertext </title>
     <link href="https://new-wayland.com/blog#Playing%20with%20Hypertext"/>
     <id>https://new-wayland.com/blog#Playing%20with%20Hypertext</id>
     <updated>2020-07-06T08:15:10Z</updated>
     <published>2020-07-06T08:01:07Z</published>
     <content><![CDATA[<p>Today I've been playing with the hypertext feature of this blog, which I hope over time will allow me to make pithy and succinct posts without having to explain terms all the time. That was sort of the point of the web in the first place and it seems to have been lost in a cloud of Javascript and fancy graphics.</p><p>For example I can now say that the Job Guarantee is really just <a class="tc-tiddlylink tc-tiddlylink-resolves" href="#QE">QE</a> of time and you can drill down to see how far the rabbit hole goes.</p><p>Let me know what other terms you want to see in the <a class="tc-tiddlylink tc-tiddlylink-resolves" href="#Glossary">Glossary</a> via the <a class="tc-tiddlylink tc-tiddlylink-resolves" href="#New%20Wayland%20Forums">New Wayland Forums</a></p>]]>
     </content>
</entry>
</feed>
