<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0">
<channel>
     <title> New Wayland Blog </title>
     <link>https://new-wayland.com/blog</link>
     <description> Welcome to the Future </description>
     <lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2020 08:11:32 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
     <title> The Indivisibility Issue </title>
     <link>https://new-wayland.com/blog#The%20Indivisibility%20Issue</link>
     <guid>https://new-wayland.com/blog#The%20Indivisibility%20Issue</guid>
     <pubDate>Sun, 09 Aug 2020 08:11:32 GMT</pubDate>
     <description><![CDATA[<p>One of the most useful, and irritating, things about computer systems is that you have to tell them precisely what to do or they won't do it. No amount of cajoling, persuasion techniques, nudge theory or other New Wave beliefs will fix a Segmentation Fault. You have to be more precise in your instructions to the machine.</p><p>While being excessively precise about limits in the New Wayland <a class="tc-tiddlylink-external" href="http://baseline.model.new-wayland.com" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">baseline model</a>, I came across something interesting I hadn't really appreciated before. </p><p>Everything on the production side has a minimum unit quantity. Half a car isn't much use. Transactions clear in whole values of the smallest unit of currency. And it takes an amount of time to create something. All of these are necessarily always above zero and even if you subdivide <em>ad absurdum</em> you hit a physical limit (one electron for one atom manipulated in one plank time).</p><p>Wages on the other hand readily hit zero - as we see regularly with intern positions, zero hour contracts, and even ultimately slavery. That again follows logically. You can either have nothing, or you can do something in the expectation that you might get more than nothing in the future. The latter is a better bet - even if it turns out to be a fallacy of composition in the aggregate. </p><p>And all this means is that even with all the &quot;friction&quot; restrictions removed in a model, it will readily drive the wage below the indivisible limits of the production system, and from which it cannot recover by &quot;natural&quot; methods. </p><p>This fits with the view <a class="tc-tiddlylink-external" href="http://neweconomicperspectives.org/2014/01/beyond-euro-left-crisis-alternative.html" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">put forward</a> by MMT stalwart Warren Mosler </p><blockquote class="tc-quote"><p>People have to work to eat, but businesses only hire when they want to, or when they think they can make a profit. It is not a fair confrontation. And if there isn’t some kind of support for labor, then real wages will be forced down continuously </p></blockquote>]]>
     </description>
</item>
<item>
     <title> Why Economists Can't See MMT </title>
     <link>https://new-wayland.com/blog#Why%20Economists%20Can't%20See%20MMT</link>
     <guid>https://new-wayland.com/blog#Why%20Economists%20Can't%20See%20MMT</guid>
     <pubDate>Sat, 08 Aug 2020 06:42:33 GMT</pubDate>
     <description><![CDATA[<p>One of the most challenging things you have to do when analysing systems is to really understand the customer's point of view. We call it &quot;obtaining Domain knowledge&quot;. Ideally you want to see the world through the other person's eyes so you can see the problems they are having and discover the best way to solve them.</p><p>And that often involves detecting blind spots where the customer simply cannot see the issue at hand, which then makes change management challenging - as you try to guide them to better ways of doing things. &quot;Trust me, I'm a Systems Specialist&quot; only gets you so far. Psychologists call this &quot;Cognitive Dissonance&quot; and it comes across as resistance to change. </p><p>It's always fascinated me why those classically trained in economics struggle with the concepts in MMT and after a few exploratory discussions I think I may have a hypothesis on at least one of those difficulties.</p><p>If a classically trained economist engages with accounting at all, they seem to do it using, what can best be described as, a General Ledger View, that seems to represent a consolidation of the entire banking system. They would appear to see a government furlough pay payment something like this.</p><p><img src="assets/banking-general-ledger.png" title="General Ledger View"></p><p>All the debits and credits add up and the payment moves from the Treasury to the deposit holder as expected. It's a transactional abstract overview of the process, and valid as far as it goes. </p><p>MMT, on the other hand, takes an institutional approach to its analysis and places the accounting within the institutional context. It also uses T-accounts rather than a general ledger which better sits with the balance sheet viewpoint it tends to take. Once you add the institutions and the balance sheet accounts to the transaction you get this view.</p><p><img src="assets/banking-t-accounts.png" title="Institutional View"></p><p>And this reveals what everybody in finance and banking understands. When government makes payments, banks get extra assets. And the banks play with those assets on the financial markets - including bidding for government bonds with them on their own behalf in addition to the customer bids <strong>using what is essentially the same amount of money</strong>.</p><p>Since you get two bids for the price of one, the government payment has clearly created something in the non-government sector that wasn't there before. </p>]]>
     </description>
</item>
<item>
     <title> How the JG Controls Inflation </title>
     <link>https://new-wayland.com/blog#How%20the%20JG%20Controls%20Inflation</link>
     <guid>https://new-wayland.com/blog#How%20the%20JG%20Controls%20Inflation</guid>
     <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jul 2020 15:02:31 GMT</pubDate>
     <description><![CDATA[<p>When you move from the JG to the private sector, government spending reduces as the private sector spending increases. This is because your wage is now paid by the private sector, not the government.</p><p>When a private sector firm goes bust, you lose your private sector wage and get a job guarantee wage - which may be lower. That increases government spending as the private sector spending is withdrawn, and nips back any boom wages that may not have been justified since the bust operation failed to push forward productivity.</p><p>Those payments and reductions are spatially targeted precisely where they are required. So you can have an area where private sector employment is increasing. Government spending on JG jobs will reduce in that area. While at the same time, the JG is increasing spending in a weak area elsewhere in the country. </p><p>That's the financial stabilisation half.</p><p>The JG wage is a fixed living income wage. It never competes on price.</p><p>Because there are people on the JG, working and turning up every day, that is a greater threat to the living wage worker in the private sector - since they can be more easily replaced if they ask for more money.</p><p>However, the worker doesn't have to put up with sweat shop wages and can move to the JG at will. So Uber et al have to pay a wage that reflects the risk and reward of the job or they won't get any labour. </p><p>Similarly if a firm tries to raise its prices because they now can't pay sweat shop wages, then that negates the &quot;non-competitive&quot; protection in the JG and JG labour can be used by social enterprises/local democracy to replace the operation trying to raise its prices.</p><p>The result is that firms that drive quantity expansion by automation are favoured. Firms can shed labour as automation proceeds, safe in the knowledge that the JG will catch those people and make sure they have a job and an income in the area they want to live in. </p><p>Demand stays up and productivity is driven forward, and that is where the higher level wage increases can come from.</p><p>That's the expectation stabilisation half.</p><p>JG is a credible threat to both workers and firms. The only degree of freedom left is to do more with less.</p><p>Both the financial half and the expectations half work together to anchor wages and prices. </p><p>Either you have an unemployment buffer doing the stabilisation (as we have now) or you have an employed buffer. The MMT analysis is that the employed buffer is superior, to the extent that it can replace the interest rate targeting mechanism we have now and base rates can be left at 0% permanently.</p><p>Which ensures mortgages remain low.</p>]]>
     </description>
</item>
<item>
     <title> Revealed: The Simple Change That Breaks Mainstream Macro </title>
     <link>https://new-wayland.com/blog#Revealed%3A%20The%20Simple%20Change%20That%20Breaks%20Mainstream%20Macro</link>
     <guid>https://new-wayland.com/blog#Revealed%3A%20The%20Simple%20Change%20That%20Breaks%20Mainstream%20Macro</guid>
     <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2020 10:11:34 GMT</pubDate>
     <description><![CDATA[<p>As regular visitors to the <a class="tc-tiddlylink-external" href="https://discord.gg/ESGqEsv" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">New Wayland Discord Forum</a> will know, I've been working on <a class="tc-tiddlylink-external" href="https://github.com/newwayland/baseline-economy" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">replicating a mainstream Baseline Model</a> (Lengnick, Matthias. (2013). Agent-based macroeconomics: A baseline model. Journal of Economic Behavior &amp; Organization. 86.10.1016/j.jebo.2012.12.021). There are <a class="tc-tiddlylink-external" href="https://github.com/newwayland/baseline-economy/blob/master/notes/issues.md" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">quite a few issues</a> with it technically but it is a good starting point. </p><p>This is a model that strips away any part of reality that get in the way of demonstrating the mainstream outcome. It has one commodity, there are no banks, money is exogenous, wages are flexible - particularly downwards, etc, etc. The paper states &quot;Finally, we demonstrated that the equilibrium is a robust result of the ACE economy for all markets. It does only break down, if either price or wage adjustment is turned off completely.&quot;</p><p>And the results appear to bear that out.</p><p><a class="tc-tiddlylink-external" href="http://baseline.model.new-wayland.com" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">(Baseline Model)</a> <img src="assets/ace-output-baseline.png" title="Baseline Output"></p><p>However when you look into the design of the model (Section 2.3, pp108) you notice something peculiar:</p><blockquote class="tc-quote"><p>Each household visits one randomly determined firm of those he has a ... connection with </p></blockquote><p>I don't know about you but I don't go to a shop randomly. I go to the one where I can get what I want at the cheapest price. Surely a good mainstream economist would do the same?</p><p>So let's make that change to this robust model. It's a single line change from</p><pre><code> # Put the preferred suppliers in a random order self.model.random.shuffle(self.preferred_suppliers)</code></pre><p>to</p><pre><code> # Put the preferred suppliers in price order self.preferred_suppliers.sort(key=attrgetter(&quot;goods_price&quot;))</code></pre><p>so rather than randomly visiting a supplier to see if they can fill our goods demand we go to the supplier with the cheapest price first and then the next cheapest and so on. </p><p>Let's see what the results are</p><p><a class="tc-tiddlylink-external" href="http://price-shopping.model.new-wayland.com" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">(Price Shopping Model)</a> <img src="assets/ace-output-price-shopping.png" title="Price Sensitive Output"></p><p>Oh dear. </p><p>If this model is to be believed, full employment/price stability and price competition appear to be incompatible in the mainstream world. </p><hr><p><sub>(Model parameters: Household Starting Money 3200, Firm Starting Money 0, Initial Goods Price 27, Initial Daily Wage Rate 70)</sub></p>]]>
     </description>
</item>
<item>
     <title> The View Through The MMT Lens </title>
     <link>https://new-wayland.com/blog#The%20View%20Through%20The%20MMT%20Lens</link>
     <guid>https://new-wayland.com/blog#The%20View%20Through%20The%20MMT%20Lens</guid>
     <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2020 10:04:22 GMT</pubDate>
     <description><![CDATA[<p>MMT is a way of looking at the financial part of the economy from a different point of view. It is often described as a Lens you can look through to see things that hither too have not been made clear. </p><p>When looking at the banking system, that view looks something like this</p><p><img src="https://docs.google.com/drawings/d/e/2PACX-1vTcQRj3bqtjzRHIcBxEevQ9NprSNoqAVbVWlrvEZOB7xMWNcJ9hToVgZ1y2siWhjR2AXrT5N8Fm6Ae-/pub?w=960&amp;amp;h=720"></p><p>What this view highlights is the institutional and accounting realities of the financial system. It is hierarchical, and in the majority of the world the central bank is a creature of the sovereign legislature, who sets its remit - the playpen in which the central bank toddler can be 'independent'. </p><p>Other entities operating in the currency zone form a hierarchy of balance sheets under the central bank. Only some have central bank accounts. Others do not. Those with central bank accounts must act as nominees for those without. This has an important effect. It means <strong>there is an extra set of financial liabilities and assets in the system for each layer in the hierarchy</strong>. If I have an account at a non-bank financial institution and I receive a government payment that will create an equivalent additional asset for the non-bank <em>and</em> the clearing bank.</p><p>For example: I get a 100GBP asset, the non-bank gets a 100GBP asset and the bank gets a 100GBP asset for the same single 100GBP transfer from HM Treasury. Everybody then gets to play asset swap games in the financial markets with their version of the asset. All three could bid at a Gilt auction for example for the single 100GBP Gilt on offer using what is essentially the same 100GBP. </p><p>That's why the banking hierarchy matters and why it is vitally important to get the institutional structure and the accounting right. You cannot just consolidate the whole thing, abstract it away and then wonder why bond auctions keep getting covered bids.</p>]]>
     </description>
</item>
<item>
     <title> MMT on The Weekly </title>
     <link>https://new-wayland.com/blog#MMT%20on%20The%20Weekly</link>
     <guid>https://new-wayland.com/blog#MMT%20on%20The%20Weekly</guid>
     <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2020 06:09:58 GMT</pubDate>
     <description><![CDATA[<p>Kudos to the Australian contingent getting this sketch on The Weekly. Can't see the BBC doing something like this - either about MMT or a decent comedy show.</p><p><html><iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="true" frameborder="0" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/uEqucQNLIko" width="560"></iframe></html></p>]]>
     </description>
</item>
<item>
     <title> The MMT Approach in a Nutshell </title>
     <link>https://new-wayland.com/blog#The%20MMT%20Approach%20in%20a%20Nutshell</link>
     <guid>https://new-wayland.com/blog#The%20MMT%20Approach%20in%20a%20Nutshell</guid>
     <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 07:46:19 GMT</pubDate>
     <description><![CDATA[<p>MMT takes the view that monetary policy is largely useless as a stabilisation device, and what is known as the horizontal circuit (&quot;bank money&quot;) should be left to operate as a market rather than being manipulated all the time. Therefore you leave the base rate at the natural rate of 0% and stop artificially trying to hold it above that, particularly stop moving it around. </p><p>What that means is that government stops paying banks &quot;welfare on reserves&quot; payments. No Interest on Reserves. No Bond Coupons. Any income banks earn they have to get by discounting collateral in the private economy and charging for that service (aka making loans).</p><p>System stabilisation can then be done using the vertical circuit (&quot;central bank money&quot;) which is added and removed as required to commercial bank's balance sheets and forcibly creates additional bank deposits in the hands of individuals - because bank money is pegged one-to-one to central bank money. </p><p>The result is that the bank money system operates within a containment vessel defined by fixed banking policies, not ones that change month to month, and the banking system ebbs and flows within the policy boundaries, with the government's vertical system countercyclically matching the ebb and flow.</p><p>This is where the Job Guarantee sits. The wage is paid with vertical money and matches the ebb and flow of bank money spending countercyclically. But importantly it does the same thing on the production side with labour hours - injecting and removing labour hours countercyclically with private and public sector demand keeping labour hours near constant relative to the working population. </p><p>A guaranteed alternative job replaces bank credit manipulation as the stabilisation process. The production system gets a change in output, not a dead loss. You get income in your pocket, not a debt millstone around your neck. </p><p>And that's how you get to true full employment and price stability within an economic system where demand is satisfied. </p>]]>
     </description>
</item>
<item>
     <title> Bonds Pay For Themselves </title>
     <link>https://new-wayland.com/blog#Bonds%20Pay%20For%20Themselves</link>
     <guid>https://new-wayland.com/blog#Bonds%20Pay%20For%20Themselves</guid>
     <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jul 2020 12:35:19 GMT</pubDate>
     <description><![CDATA[<p>I note that the Hard of Accounting are out in force again pushing their fallacious line that Taxes Must Rise because we decided to use government to save the economy in the face of a nasty pandemic.</p><p>There must be Fire and Brimstone. The Sin must be Purged.</p><p>Clueless idiots the lot of them - particularly those at the ironically named Institute for Fiscal Studies who really ought to know better. (If they do study Fiscal they don't do it very effectively).</p><p>This is how it works in reality.</p><p>You receive some furlough pay, which is taxed, you spend that money at a shop, which is taxed, they pay their staff which is taxed, who spend that money at a shop, which is taxed and so on. </p><p>Imagine a stone skipping across a pond where every bounce is a transaction and every ripple is taxation. </p><p>If you expand that sequence you'll find that eventually the initial injection of money (G) for the furlough pay disappears in taxation (T). Or as it tends to be written mathematically:</p><p><span><span class="katex-display"><span class="katex"><span class="katex-mathml"><math><semantics><mrow><mi>δ</mi><mo stretchy="false">(</mo><mi>G</mi><mo>−</mo><mi>T</mi><mo stretchy="false">)</mo><mo>=</mo><mn>0</mn></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex"> \delta(G - T) = 0 </annotation></semantics></math></span><span class="katex-html" aria-hidden="true"><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1em;vertical-align:-0.25em;"></span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.03785em;">δ</span><span class="mopen">(</span><span class="mord mathdefault">G</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span><span class="mbin">−</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1em;vertical-align:-0.25em;"></span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.13889em;">T</span><span class="mclose">)</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span><span class="mrel">=</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:0.64444em;vertical-align:0em;"></span><span class="mord">0</span></span></span></span></span></span></p><p>Bonds come about when not everybody in the sequence spends all their money - aka saving. There's been a lot of that recently due to frightened people increasing their rainy day funds, people paying off loans and simple lack of opportunities to spend.</p><p>The increase in Savings (S) and decrease in Loans (I) creates a government deficit. Or as I like to write it</p><p><span><span class="katex-display"><span class="katex"><span class="katex-mathml"><math><semantics><mrow><mi>δ</mi><mo stretchy="false">(</mo><mi>S</mi><mo>−</mo><mi>I</mi><mo stretchy="false">)</mo><mtext>  </mtext><mo>⟹</mo><mtext>  </mtext><mi>δ</mi><mo stretchy="false">(</mo><mi>G</mi><mo>−</mo><mi>T</mi><mo stretchy="false">)</mo></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex"> \delta(S - I) \implies \delta(G -T) </annotation></semantics></math></span><span class="katex-html" aria-hidden="true"><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1em;vertical-align:-0.25em;"></span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.03785em;">δ</span><span class="mopen">(</span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.05764em;">S</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span><span class="mbin">−</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1em;vertical-align:-0.25em;"></span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.07847em;">I</span><span class="mclose">)</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span><span class="mrel">⟹</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1em;vertical-align:-0.25em;"></span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.03785em;">δ</span><span class="mopen">(</span><span class="mord mathdefault">G</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span><span class="mbin">−</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1em;vertical-align:-0.25em;"></span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.13889em;">T</span><span class="mclose">)</span></span></span></span></span></span></p><p>A change in net savings causes a change in the government sector deficit</p><p>Under our current regime that deficit is swapped for Bonds. Green Dollars are swapped for Yellow Dollars (treasuries), Silver Pounds are swapped for Gold Pounds (Gilts). </p><p>The Treasury or the Gilt or the JGB is just a savings instrument held by somebody who didn't feel like spending their money right now. </p><p>In our stone bouncing sequence above you can imagine the video is paused just after a ripple occurs. A Bond is a pause button in the spending sequence. </p><p>Eventually the sunny uplands will return, people will feel less frightened, go to the shops more, and break out the credit card again. And that is like hitting 'play' on our sequence. The saved money is then spent at a shop, which is taxed, who pay their staff, which is taxed, who then spend at the shop, which is taxed... The bouncing continues, creating a decrease in savings and/or an increase in Loans. Which gives:</p><p><span><span class="katex-display"><span class="katex"><span class="katex-mathml"><math><semantics><mrow><mi>δ</mi><mo stretchy="false">(</mo><mi>S</mi><mo>−</mo><mi>I</mi><mo stretchy="false">)</mo><mtext>  </mtext><mo>⟹</mo><mtext>  </mtext><mi>δ</mi><mo stretchy="false">(</mo><mn>0</mn><mo>−</mo><mi>T</mi><mo stretchy="false">)</mo></mrow><annotation encoding="application/x-tex"> \delta(S - I) \implies \delta(0-T) </annotation></semantics></math></span><span class="katex-html" aria-hidden="true"><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1em;vertical-align:-0.25em;"></span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.03785em;">δ</span><span class="mopen">(</span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.05764em;">S</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span><span class="mbin">−</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1em;vertical-align:-0.25em;"></span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.07847em;">I</span><span class="mclose">)</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span><span class="mrel">⟹</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2777777777777778em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1em;vertical-align:-0.25em;"></span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.03785em;">δ</span><span class="mopen">(</span><span class="mord">0</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span><span class="mbin">−</span><span class="mspace" style="margin-right:0.2222222222222222em;"></span></span><span class="base"><span class="strut" style="height:1em;vertical-align:-0.25em;"></span><span class="mord mathdefault" style="margin-right:0.13889em;">T</span><span class="mclose">)</span></span></span></span></span></span></p><p>A reduction in net savings causes additional tax!</p><p>And there, by accounting identity, is your extra tax, which reduces the government deficit and may even eliminate it completely and create a surplus. The extra tax ensures that bonds that mature are not reissued and the rate of issue of bonds slows downs and may even reverse.</p><p>The tax arises and the bonds disappear completely automatically when people who hold the savings they represent decide to spend their savings. </p><p>The same percentage of a bigger number is another bigger number. Mathematics will still work as it always has done post-Covid.</p><p>No raid on wallets required. </p>]]>
     </description>
</item>
<item>
     <title> UK Employment stats </title>
     <link>https://new-wayland.com/blog#UK%20Employment%20stats</link>
     <guid>https://new-wayland.com/blog#UK%20Employment%20stats</guid>
     <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jul 2020 09:32:34 GMT</pubDate>
     <description><![CDATA[<p>If this wiki does it job, then <a class="tc-tiddlylink tc-tiddlylink-resolves" href="#UK%20-%20People%20Wanting%20Work">UK - People Wanting Work</a> should give you the current up to date UK job shortage statistics. </p><p>And that page should always be up to date - if I've remembered to update the underlying spreadsheet!</p><p>Searching for 'stats' in the search box will bring up all the wiki pages referencing the statistics I keep</p>]]>
     </description>
</item>
<item>
     <title> From Furlough to Full-Employment - Part Deux </title>
     <link>https://new-wayland.com/blog#From%20Furlough%20to%20Full-Employment%20-%20Part%20Deux</link>
     <guid>https://new-wayland.com/blog#From%20Furlough%20to%20Full-Employment%20-%20Part%20Deux</guid>
     <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 07:26:25 GMT</pubDate>
     <description><![CDATA[<p>The idea is to provide real people with the ability to sell their hours automatically.</p><p>In my current design you are always on the default PAYE scheme, which kicks in as soon as fewer than 35 hours are booked to another PAYE scheme. That drops you onto the &quot;volunteer list&quot; for the unbooked hours doing the &quot;looking for a JG position&quot; job by default (a rather more useful version of the current 35 hours &quot;job seeking&quot; requirement of Universal Credit - looking for jobs that cannot exist in aggregate).</p><p>You can then contact a Work Coach to have yourself taken off that job if you'd prefer not to bother with the process, or to investigate what is on offer and get something lined up. If you don't contact a Work Coach, or they can't easily contact you, then they will suspend payment until you do. Just as would happen if you didn't turn up to work in any other job. I want the process to be automatic, and the registration and verification details submitted in the PAYE Returns by the previous PAYE employer. No forms to fill in.</p><p>Running through the usual use cases I believe this process handles full-time, part-time and temporary, whether they want to be engaged with the Job Guarantee or not.</p><p>Beyond that it's up to you. But you only get paid for hours booked to the Job Guarantee. Since there is a job on offer, you will take it if you are short of money. If you're not short of money and have savings or redundancy then you can take your time. Those with scarce skills higher up the tree will be able to negotiate those protections into their employment contracts - particularly if they unionise.</p><p>How long you can be on the &quot;looking for a JG position&quot; job before you are required to move on I've not really thought about very much (largely because I suspect everybody will want to get off it as soon as possible). I don't believe there is a time limit in Universal Credit, but given the higher level of payment on the Job Guarantee perhaps you will have to put your case to a jury of your peers after a period of time - particularly if you can choose to go on the JG.</p>]]>
     </description>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
